Guide to the Martha O. Adams papers RL.11341
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Martha O. Adams papers
1960-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Adams, Martha O.
RL.11341
16 Linear Feet
Martha Olds Adams is an American writer and poet. Her works center primarily on the areas of feminist theology, female spirituality and social justice. The Martha O. Adams papers contain her poetry collections and other writings; correspondence and ephemera related to her publications, workshops and speaking engagements, as well as documentation of her research and activist work.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials require reformatting before use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Martha O. Adams papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Biographical / Historical
Martha Olds Adams is a writer and poet based in Hendersonville, NC. She was inspired when introduced to the works of Christian feminist theologians and the idea of the divine feminine. She participated in the Hartford Seminary Women's Leadership Institute in 1997 and contributed to a legacy of expression of female spirituality by organizing retreats and writing poetry.
She has written three poetry collections including: Buried Seed (2015), What Your Heart Needs to Know (2008) and Peeling the Rind (2000). She also wrote an epic poem for Readers' Theater entitled She Rises Through the Sickle Moon, that portrays the voices of over 100 "historical daughters of the divine mother." Her works center on feminist theology, diversity and global justice. She performs her poems across the country, including frequent readings hosted at the Hendersonville Public Library. Adams also wrote Courage for Those Who Care (1999) based on her father's experience with Alzheimer's disease.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Adams' personal writings and works, ephemera related to her publications, items associated with retreats, workshops and speaking engagements, research about influential female figures and her involvement in issues such as reproductive rights, voting rights, and feminist theology. The collection also includes personal and professional correspondence, educational materials from Adams' participation in the Hartford Seminary Leadership Institute as well as reflections on her father's struggle with Alzheimer's disease. There is also an Audio/Visual Materials series that contains interviews and documentary materials, as well as digital backups of Adams' writings, works, and correspondence.
Feminist theology; Feminism -- Poetry.; Women and religion -- Southern States; Spirituality -- Women; Alzheimer's disease; Women poets; American poetry -- Women authors; Audiovisual materials; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Writings and Works, 1983-2016
  Scope and Contents
  Adams' personal writings and works, including all of her poetry collections in various stages of development from hard written copy to final edition.
  - Biography and List of Published Works, 2016 (Box 11)
  - Invisible In My Bones, 1995-2016; 5 folders (Box 1, Box 3)
  - What Your Heart Needs to Know, 2008; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Voices Near and Far, June 7, 1994 (Box 1)
  - She Rises Through the Sickle Moon Play, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Sacred Space, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Courage for Those Who Care, 1999; 5 folders (Box 2, Box 3, Box 10)
  - Peeling the Rind Exhibit - NWSA Conference, 2003 (Box 2)
  - The Unanswered Questions, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Marguarite, March 30, 1995 (Box 2)
  - In Your Meadow: A Meditation With Art, For Coloring, 2016; 5 folders (Box 2, Box 10)
  - Womansong (Box 3)
  - Cakes for the Queen of Heaven, 1986; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Created in Her Image: Models of the Feminine Divine, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Gateway (Box 10)
  - Buried Seed, 2015; 2 folders (Box 10)
- Events, 1988-2016
  Contains ephemera related to Adams' publications and items associated with retreats, workshops and speaking engagements about spirituality, poetry, and other subjects.
  - Dissident Daughter Rituals (Box 4)
  - Woman Spirit Retreat, 1997-2006; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Personal Energy Discernment Workshop (Box 5)
  - Global Gardening Celebration, 1988-2001 (Box 5)
  - Henderson County Public Library Programs, 2004-2012; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - The Artists' Way, 1998-2000 (Box 5)
  - Chi Omega Round Robin (Box 5)
  - Women, Word & The Church, 1987-1994 (Box 5)
  - A Celebration of Women in the Arts, March 22, 2000 (Box 5)
  - An Evening of Poetry, October 19, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Woman Spirit Mask, 2 folders (Box 11)
- Activism and Feminist Scholarship, 1960-2000
  Consists of Adams' research about influential female figures and her involvement in issues such as reproductive rights, voting rights, feminist theology, educational materials from Adams' participation in the Hartford Seminary Leadership Institute, as well as reflections on her father's struggle with Alzheimer's disease.
  - New Conversations: Abortion and Reproductive Rights (Box 6)
  - Bless Sophia: Worship, Liturgy and Ritual of the Re-Imagining Community, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Re-Imagining Quarterly Newsletter, nos. 4-5, 7, 9, 11, 21, 27, 30, 1994-2003 (Box 6)
  - Re-Imagining Publicity, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Housatonic College Visit, 2009 (Box 6)
  - Awakenings, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Painted paper mache "Awakenings" ritual mask with artist's statement (Box 11)
  - On The Privilege of Voting (Box 7)
  - Converse College Course on Women and Religion, May 9, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Notable American Women (Box 7)
  - Women Sketches (Box 7)
  - Made in Her Image Facilitator Guide (Box 7)
  - Made in Her Image Participant Resource Book (Box 7)
  - Carol Castle (Box 7)
  - Church Sermons and Discussion: Feminist Theology (Box 7)
  - Women in the World: Ending Discrimination (Box 7)
  - News Clippings on Women and Theology, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Scholarly Writing: Feminist Theology (Box 7)
  - Common Lot, 1990-1996 (Box 7)
  - Hartford Seminary Women's Leadership Institute, 1996-1997; 10 folders (Box 8)
  - Book Reviews (Box 8)
  - Coping with AD Abyss, December 14, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Alliance Review Article, July 2, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Resources on AD and Dementia (Box 8)
  - Notes for presentations on AD (Box 8)
  - Yale Divinity School presentation, March 1997 (Box 8)
  - Kenmure's Quality of Life Program, August 31, 2000 (Box 8)
  - Mt. of Connecticut Alzheimer's Association, June 1990 (Box 8)
  - Caregiving: Part of the Journey (Box 8)
  - U of Bridgeport Conference on AD, May 20, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Caregiving for the Alz. Afflicted, March 1997 (Box 8)
  - Alz. Association Conference, April 28, 2000 (Box 8)
  - The Mother Jones Manual (Adams editor) (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1975-2008
  Primarily personal correspondence, but also includes book reviews and letters from readers.
  - Christmas Letters, 1987-2008 (Box 9)
  - Henderson County Public Library (Box 9)
  - Alzheimer's (Box 9)
  - Elizabeth Bettenhausen (Box 9)
  - Personal Correnspondence, 1979-2016; 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Letters From Readers, 1984-1999; 2 folders (Box 9)
- Audio/Visual Materials, 1989-2009
  Contains interviews and documentary materials, as well as digital backups of Adams' writings, works, and correspondence.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audio/visual materials must be reformatted before use.
  - Re-Imaging Conference, 1993; 3 audiocassettes (Box 10)
  - Alzheimer's Interview, March 19, 1989; 1 audiocassettes (Box 10)
  - Girl Talk, 2005; 4 cdrs (Box 10)
  - Unity Groove Interview, October 28, 2009; 1 cdrs (Box 10)
  - Call to Courage Audiobook (Box 10)
  - Call to Courage, 1999; 7 disks (Box 10)
  - Invisible In My Bones, 15 discs (Box 10)
  - Poetry, 1998-2009; 7 disks (Box 10)
  - Mary Johnson Olds Project, 1 discs (Box 10)
  - What Your Heart Needs to Know, 1 discs (Box 10)
  - She Rises Through the Sickle Moon, 3 discs (Box 10)
  - Hartford Seminary, 3 discs (Box 10)
  - Artists' Way, 1998; 1 discs (Box 10)
  - Personal Letters, 1997-1999; 1 discs (Box 10)
  - Woman Spirit, 2001-2004; 2 discs (Box 10)
  - Buried Seed, 1 cdrs (Box 10)